<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Thibaud’s blog]]></title>
  <link href="https://thib.me/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://thib.me/"/>
  <updated>2022-11-08T23:42:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://thib.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Thibaud Colas]]></name>
    
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Outreachy: welcoming new contributors to open source]]></title>
    <link href="https://thib.me/outreachy-welcoming-new-contributors-to-open-source"/>
    <updated>2022-10-10T18:50:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://thib.me/outreachy-welcoming-new-contributors-to-open-source</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the first time, Wagtail is joining Outreachy’s open source internships program</p>

<!-- more -->

<p><img src="/images/blog/outreachy-welcoming-new-contributors-to-open-source/outreachy-banner.jpg" alt="Outreachy - Internships supporting diversity in Free and Open Source Software" /></p>

<p>As an experienced open source contributor, onboarding newcomers into the world of open source is amongst the most rewarding tasks. After a successful participation to <a href="https://wagtail.org/blog/google-summer-of-code-2022-wagtail-midterm/">this year’s Google Summer of Code</a>, we’re back at it already with <a href="https://www.outreachy.org/">Outreachy</a>, joining their December 2022 cohort.</p>

<h2 id="what-is-outreachy">What is Outreachy</h2>

<p>Outreachy provides <strong>internships in open source and open science.</strong> The program provides internships to people subject to systemic bias and impacted by under-representation in the technical industry where they are living. Internships are fully remote, over 3 months, with interns receiving a fair stipend to support their work.</p>

<p>For Wagtail, this type of program is one of the best ways to work with more diverse contributors. We’re elated to have been selected, and hope we’ll get to work with between one and three new contributors this year.</p>

<h2 id="the-project-ideas">The project ideas</h2>

<p>Compared to Google Summer of Code, Outreachy only allows mentors to propose project ideas, rather than candidates. We’ve earmarked three project ideas.</p>

<h3 id="a-built-in-accessibility-checker-for-wagtail">A built-in accessibility checker for Wagtail</h3>

<p>This project is fundamental to meeting our <a href="https://wagtail.org/accessibility/">accessibility commitments</a>. The primary goal is to integrate an existing accessibility test suite within the CMS in a way that takes advantage of the tool’s capabilities and Wagtail’s UI specificities. We envision this being part of Wagtail’s content previews: as the page content changes, authors see what the published page would look like, and get feedback on accessibility issues.</p>

<p>Here is a sneak peak at our first prototype:</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/outreachy-welcoming-new-contributors-to-open-source/sa11y-prototype.png" alt="Screenshot of a prototype accessibility checker built into Wagtail's live preview" /></p>

<p><em>For more information about this project, to ask questions and provide feedback, follow</em> <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail/discussions/9262"><em>discussion #9262 Built-in Accessibility Checker</em></a><em> on GitHub.</em></p>

<h3 id="improving-wagtails-editor-guide">Improving Wagtail’s editor guide</h3>

<p>This project follows through <a href="https://wagtail.org/blog/google-summer-of-code-wagtail-editor-guide/">Hitansh Shah’s GSoC project</a>, where he created a new site for the Editor Guide documentation, with support from the project mentors. The new site looks fabulous:</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/outreachy-welcoming-new-contributors-to-open-source/editor-guide.png" alt="Editor Guide landing page before-after" /></p>

<p>Now the next step is simply to revamp the content! This wasn’t part of Hitansh’s project, and is the perfect follow-up. We’re also very happy to propose a project idea where there is <strong>no need for contributors to know how to code</strong>.</p>

<p><em>For more information about this project, to ask questions and provide feedback, follow <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/guide/discussions/116">discussion #116 Outreachy: Improve user guide documentation for Wagtail</a>.</em></p>

<h3 id="stimulus-for-interactive-widgets-in-wagtail">Stimulus for interactive widgets in Wagtail</h3>

<p>Following the leadership of our contributor LB, our UI team has been carefully considering how to bring Wagtail’s JavaScript interactivity to modern standards. This project is the natural follow-up to LB’s excellent <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/rfcs/pull/78">RFC #78 for us to adopt Stimulus</a>: rolling it out across large swaths of the user interface.</p>

<p>The RFC is still going through the last stages of validation, so is the best way to follow up or comment on this project!</p>

<h2 id="how-to-participate">How to participate</h2>

<p>For aspiring newcomers already accepted in the December 2022 Outreachy cohort, head over to our <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail/wiki/Outreachy-2022">Outreachy 2022 wiki page</a> for more information about Wagtail, good resources, and a list of initial tasks.</p>

<p>For everyone else, we’d love to hear your thoughts on the project ideas, and are also actively looking for additional support so we can confidently take on all three projects. Join us in #outreachy on <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail/wiki/Slack">Wagtail’s Slack workspace</a>.</p>

<h2 id="whats-next">What’s next</h2>

<p>We hope to hear from a lot of newcomers through the <a href="https://www.outreachy.org/docs/community/#current-timeline">initial contribution period</a>, where candidates get to know different communities and apply to projects. We’ll make sure to share more information about projects that are going ahead and their respective contributors once details are confirmed, towards the end of November.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Google Summer of Code 2022 for Wagtail]]></title>
    <link href="https://thib.me/google-summer-of-code-2022-for-wagtail"/>
    <updated>2022-07-14T18:50:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://thib.me/google-summer-of-code-2022-for-wagtail</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This year, Wagtail gets to take part in Google Summer of Code independently!</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>We are participating with three projects:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail/discussions/8193">Contrast Themes by Anuja Raj Verma</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail/discussions/7824">Editor’s Guide - A standalone project by Hitansh Shah</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail/discussions/8156">Toolkit for StreamField data migrations in Wagtail by Sandil Ranasinghe</a></li>
</ul>

<p>And we have a fourth project independently sponsored by Torchbox: <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail/discussions/8158">UX Unification by Paarth Agarwal</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[MiXiT 2022: The 97.4% North Star]]></title>
    <link href="https://thib.me/the-97-4-percent-north-star"/>
    <updated>2022-05-25T08:50:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://thib.me/the-97-4-percent-north-star</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Slides for my <a href="https://mixitconf.org/fr/2022/the-97-4-north-star">MiXiT 2022 talk</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/726166919?h=c0d26f9453&amp;title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1SdXC4eiPqhK3gvdV9pMsarEHqSzooPoUxRVoJrBT3iQ/edit?usp=sharing">Google Slides; The 97.4% North Star - Thibaud Colas - MiXiT 2022</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1TjCmQdEKC3pQ12N_ifRgGnReAnzvAGv_/view?usp=sharing">PDF export (4MB); The 97.4% North Star - Thibaud Colas - MiXiT 2022</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1nGrmreQjwP3be5Y0LNW-WPU4lLv1Qsv5nozlBvEZQkw/edit?usp=sharing">Plain-text export; The 97.4% North Star - Thibaud Colas - MiXiT 2022</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The State of Wagtail - Wagtail Space US 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://thib.me/state-of-wagtail-wagtail-space-us-2022"/>
    <updated>2022-03-24T16:20:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://thib.me/state-of-wagtail-wagtail-space-us-2022</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here are the slides and my notes for my <a href="https://us.wagtail.space/">Wagtail Space US 2022</a> talk <a href="https://youtu.be/tttOiW_bSYM">State of Wagtail</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Slides:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1XHkr0ijLX9b0YwQIXdshL51-J8cSH07tPm3jPWIk_eA/edit">Google Slides: State of Wagtail - Wagtail Space US 2022</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1rW_uhz4WuVOnv-KsvuldmLSO-r_DrVfu/view">PDF: State of Wagtail - Wagtail Space US 2022</a></li>
</ul>

<iframe title="(my) State of Wagtail – Thibaud Colas, Wagtail Space US 2022" width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/tttOiW_bSYM" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[State of Wagtail’s accessibility]]></title>
    <link href="https://thib.me/state-of-wagtail-accessibility"/>
    <updated>2022-02-28T07:42:03+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://thib.me/state-of-wagtail-accessibility</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After <a href="https://wagtail.org/blog/announcing-wagtail-sub-teams/">6 months of operations</a>, we reflect on the progress our <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail/wiki/Wagtail-sub-teams#accessibility">accessibility team</a> has made, and go on the lookout for new contributors.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Accessibility has been on Wagtail’s roadmap for quite some time, and we’ve <a href="https://wagtail.org/blog/accessibility-team-reloaded/">reflected on our progress</a> in the past. Now’s a good time for us to do this again, and share our plans for the next few years.</p>

<h3 id="what-we-achieved-in-2021">What we achieved in 2021</h3>

<p>2021 has been a busy year for Wagtail’s <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail/wiki/Accessibility-team">accessibility team</a>. With 5 members on board last February, and <a href="https://github.com/SaptakS">Saptak Sengupta</a> joining us in July, we went through a lot of long-awaited changes.</p>

<ul>
  <li>We now have an <a href="https://wagtail.org/accessibility/">official accessibility statement</a>. This was the first time we publicly stated ATAG 2.0 as a conformance goal.</li>
  <li>We also published our <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1l7tnpEyJiC5BWE_JX0XCkknyrjxYA5T2aee5JgPnmi4/edit#gid=1433484179">(work in progress) accessibility audit</a>. It’s far from complete, but has already helped us prioritise specific improvements to the CMS.</li>
  <li>We made a big push to improve support for Windows high contrast mode as part of <a href="https://docs.wagtail.org/en/stable/releases/2.15.html#windows-high-contrast-support">Wagtail 2.15</a>.</li>
  <li>We were also involved with the development of large features, earlier than might have been the case in the past.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="windows-high-contrast-mode">Windows high-contrast mode</h3>

<p>This significant effort is worth highlighting for a few reasons:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The whole backlog of improvement came from a <a href="https://trello.com/b/MnlPSvkD/wagtail-high-contrast">large audit</a> by <a href="https://github.com/kbayliss">Kyle Bayliss</a>, which allowed us to understand the bigger picture of which practices in our development might be causing issues.</li>
  <li>In contrast, we were able to split the fixes <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail/issues?q=is%3Aissue+sort%3Aupdated-desc+label%3A%22good+first+issue%22+label%3AAccessibility+is%3Aclosed+High-contrast+mode">over multiple tickets</a> to make those potential contributions more accessible to newcomers (in total, 12 people participated in those changes!).</li>
  <li>We got a sponsorship from <a href="https://assistivlabs.com/">Assistiv Labs</a> to simplify testing of Wagtail with different assistive technologies. Windows high contrast mode in particular was very hard for us to test until then.</li>
</ul>

<p>There is still a long way to go for us to achieve full support, but we feel better able to deliver this than ever. Here is what Windows high contrast mode looks like in Wagtail currently, tested via Assistiv Labs:</p>

<p><a href="/images/blog/state-of-wagtail-accessibility/whcm-wagtail.png"><img src="/images/blog/state-of-wagtail-accessibility/whcm-wagtail.png" alt="Screenshot of Windows high contrast mode in Assistiv Labs, with the main navigation opened over page listings" /></a></p>

<h3 id="what-we-didnt-achieve">What we didn’t achieve</h3>

<ul>
  <li>We were hoping to have accessibility team <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2021/Feb/19/office-hours/">office hours</a>, and never got round to starting this. If you would be interested, please <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail/wiki/Slack">let us know on Slack in #accessibility</a>!</li>
  <li>One of the key features we wanted to scope was accessibility testing built into the CMS – we made plans internally, but didn’t draft a formal proposal as we had hoped. More on that soon!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-year-ahead">The year ahead</h2>

<p>The elephant in the room for Wagtail’s accessibility improvements is the <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail/discussions/7739">Page editor 2022</a> project, which accessibility team members are heavily involved with. This marks a clear transition for us: from frequently fixing issues piecemeal after the fact; to being involved in every feature’s planning, making sure accessibility is considered.</p>

<p>We also get to direct the scope of the project – for example, recommending a wholesale replacement of the current datepicker, rather than a restyling.</p>

<p>A practical example of our involvement is the production of annotations for UI semantics and behavior, following the <a href="https://dribbble.com/shots/6269661-Accessibility-Bluelines">Accessibility Bluelines</a> methodology:</p>

<p><a href="/images/blog/state-of-wagtail-accessibility/accessibility-bluelines.png"><img src="/images/blog/state-of-wagtail-accessibility/accessibility-bluelines.png" alt="Accessibility bluelines example for Wagtail, annotating the sidebar and top of the page editor" /></a></p>

<h3 id="accessibility-of-the-cms">Accessibility of the CMS</h3>

<p>We are and will be going through a lot of improvements:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Liaising with the Page editor 2022 project, and other features development, so accessibility requirements are included.</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail/pull/7751">Automated accessibility testing</a> of all pull requests, so ongoing QA isn’t as reliant on manual testing.</li>
  <li>Rolling out the most important accessibility-related changes from the page editor project, to the rest of the CMS.</li>
</ul>

<p>We will also keep up with <a href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/standards-guidelines/wcag/new-in-22/">WCAG 2.2</a>’s publication, and drafts of <a href="https://w3c.github.io/silver/guidelines/">WCAG 3.0</a>.</p>

<h3 id="accessibility-of-sites-built-with-wagtail">Accessibility of sites built with Wagtail</h3>

<p>The biggest change here will be the inclusion of built-in accessibility tests, as part of page previews when editing content. This is par for the course of ATAG 2.0 conformance, and we’re also gradually integrating findings from the <a href="https://accessibilitycluster.com/">We4Authors Cluster</a> research project, which details the most important accessibility features in content management systems.</p>

<h2 id="how-you-can-help">How you can help</h2>

<p>Two things:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Regularly <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail/discussions/7739">provide feedback on the Page editor 2022</a> project, based on your experience with Wagtail and other content management systems.</li>
  <li>Consider joining our accessibility team! We are looking for new members for the next 6 months or so, from all backgrounds, all skillsets.</li>
</ul>

<p>In both cases, we’re particularly keen to hear from people who:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Have personal experience of access and functional needs, or who are regular users of assistive technologies.</li>
  <li>Work on UX, design, or content – and can help us understand the needs of our users.</li>
</ul>

<p>To chat to the accessibility team directly, reach out to us <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail/wiki/Slack">on Slack in #accessibility</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Adding Prettier onto an existing project]]></title>
    <link href="https://thib.me/adding-prettier-existing-project"/>
    <updated>2022-02-04T21:18:03+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://thib.me/adding-prettier-existing-project</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://prettier.io/">Prettier</a> is good. So good, it’s easy to get used to it, and subsequently want to retrofit it onto existing projects. Here’s a step-by-step guide and example: configuring and documenting Prettier and reformatting existing code, all the while making sure not to break other people’s work.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="the-example">The example</h2>

<p>All the steps described below are demonstrated publicly in a real-world project: Wagtail, via issue <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail/issues/6059">#6059 Automatic code formatting with Prettier</a>. The implementation was split into two PRs: <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail/pull/7908">#7908 Add Prettier configuration &amp; documentation</a>, <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail/pull/7912">#7912 Prettier reformatting</a>, and finally one extra commit, <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail/commit/7eb8730d7372dc6b4752308a7e3354b36810f32e">7eb8730d7372dc6b4752308a7e3354b36810f32e</a>.</p>

<p>Finally, here are <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail/issues/6059#issuecomment-1029941428">instructions on resolving conflicts</a> that weren’t directly stored in the repository (as this is a one-off task).</p>

<h2 id="why-two-prs-and-a-commit">Why two PRs and a commit</h2>

<p>I recommend always splitting the addition of any formatting tool into at least two PRs and the extra commit:</p>

<ol>
  <li>The first PR takes care of anything that requires careful review – configuration, integrations, documentation.</li>
  <li>The second PR takes care of the actual reformatting.</li>
  <li>Finally, the final commit is just there to finish setting up the <a href="https://git-scm.com/docs/git-blame#Documentation/git-blame.txt---ignore-revs-fileltfilegt"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.git-blame-ignore-revs</code> file for git’s <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ignoreRevsFile</code></a>.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="configuration">Configuration</h2>

<p>This is actually the simplest step.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Update the project’s <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.editorconfig</code> first, as Prettier reads it (<a href="https://github.com/thibaudcolas/cookbook/blob/main/.editorconfig">here’s an example</a>).</li>
  <li>Create a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">prettier.config.js</code> with any desired options.</li>
  <li>Create a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.prettierignore</code>. I’d recommend to add large folders in here to speed up Prettier looking for files when using very broad glob patterns.</li>
</ul>

<p>Personally I’ll always prefer to set all configuration options, even when using defaults. This saves having to remember what options are available that might not be set on the particular project when re-reviewing the configuration. I also always prefer using JavaScript for configuration – syntax highlighting and auto-formatting are dependable.</p>

<h3 id="which-languages-should-i-use-prettier-for">Which languages should I use Prettier for?</h3>

<p>I’d recommend all languages that Prettier supports, potentially with the exception of Markdown. Although the reformatting is excellent, enforcing a single format for documentation often feels cumbersome – particularly if the project’s documentation might often be updated by contributors with little knowledge of the project’s tooling.</p>

<p>If a supported language isn’t used, make sure to add its extension to the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.prettierignore</code> so the files are consistently skipped. Here’s an example:</p>

<div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c"># Irrelevant files ignored for performance reasons.</span>
node_modules
public/
coverage/
vendor/
static
_build
<span class="c"># File types which Prettier supports but we don’t want auto-formatting.</span>
<span class="k">*</span>.md
<span class="c"># Files which contain incompatible syntax.</span>
<span class="k">*</span>.html
wagtail/admin/templates/wagtailadmin/edit_handlers/inline_panel.js
</code></pre></div></div>

<h2 id="integrations">Integrations</h2>

<p>I’ll always start with the same two commands:</p>

<div class="language-json highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="w">  </span><span class="nl">"format"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"prettier --write '**/?(.)*.{css,scss,js,ts,tsx,json,yaml,yml}'"</span><span class="err">,</span><span class="w">
  </span><span class="nl">"lint:format"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"prettier --check '**/?(.)*.{css,scss,js,ts,tsx,json,yaml,yml}'"</span><span class="w">
</span></code></pre></div></div>

<p>The glob pattern might seem complicated – it’s wrapped in single quotes to prevent shell globbing (thus making it consistent cross-platform). It uses <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">**/?(.)*</code> so files are checked at all directory levels in the current folder, and regardless of whether file names start with a dot or not.</p>

<p>As to where those commands should run – generally in continuous integration, potentially in Git pre-commit hooks.</p>

<h3 id="pre-commit">pre-commit</h3>

<p>With the confusingly-named <a href="https://pre-commit.com/">pre-commit framework</a>, it looks like:</p>

<div class="language-yaml highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="pi">-</span> <span class="na">repo</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">https://github.com/pre-commit/mirrors-prettier</span>
  <span class="na">rev</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">v2.5.1</span>
  <span class="na">hooks</span><span class="pi">:</span>
    <span class="pi">-</span> <span class="na">id</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">prettier</span>
      <span class="na">types_or</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="pi">[</span><span class="nv">css</span><span class="pi">,</span> <span class="nv">scss</span><span class="pi">,</span> <span class="nv">javascript</span><span class="pi">,</span> <span class="nv">ts</span><span class="pi">,</span> <span class="nv">tsx</span><span class="pi">,</span> <span class="nv">json</span><span class="pi">,</span> <span class="nv">yaml</span><span class="pi">]</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Note <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">types_or</code> aren’t always file extensions, they’re <a href="https://github.com/pre-commit/identify/blob/master/identify/extensions.py">arbitrary identifiers</a> for some languages.</p>

<p>Here’s what I personally prefer – just bash:</p>

<div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c">#!/usr/bin/env bash</span>

<span class="c"># Fail on first line that fails.</span>
<span class="nb">set</span> <span class="nt">-e</span>

<span class="c"># Only keep staged files that are added (A), copied (C) or modified (M).</span>
<span class="nv">STAGED</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="si">$(</span>git <span class="nt">--no-pager</span> diff <span class="nt">--name-only</span> <span class="nt">--cached</span> <span class="nt">--diff-filter</span><span class="o">=</span>ACM<span class="si">)</span>
<span class="c"># Files which are only partly staged (eg. git add --patch).</span>
<span class="nv">PATCH_STAGED</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="si">$(</span>git <span class="nt">--no-pager</span> diff <span class="nt">--name-only</span> <span class="nt">--diff-filter</span><span class="o">=</span>ACM <span class="nv">$STAGED</span><span class="si">)</span>
<span class="c"># Files which are fully staged.</span>
<span class="nv">FULLY_STAGED</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="si">$(</span><span class="nb">comm</span> <span class="nt">-23</span> &lt;<span class="o">(</span><span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="nv">$STAGED</span><span class="s2">"</span><span class="o">)</span> &lt;<span class="o">(</span><span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="nv">$PATCH_STAGED</span><span class="s2">"</span><span class="o">)</span><span class="si">)</span>

<span class="nv">PRETTIER_STAGED</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="si">$(</span><span class="nb">grep</span> <span class="nt">-E</span> <span class="s1">'.(css|scss|js|ts|tsx|json|yaml|yml)$'</span> <span class="o">&lt;&lt;&lt;</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="nv">$STAGED</span><span class="s2">"</span> <span class="o">||</span> <span class="nb">true</span><span class="si">)</span>
<span class="nv">PRETTIER_FULLY_STAGED</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="si">$(</span><span class="nb">grep</span> <span class="nt">-E</span> <span class="s1">'.(css|scss|js|ts|tsx|json|yaml|yml)$'</span> <span class="o">&lt;&lt;&lt;</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="nv">$FULLY_STAGED</span><span class="s2">"</span> <span class="o">||</span> <span class="nb">true</span><span class="si">)</span>

<span class="c"># Format and re-stage fully staged files only.</span>
<span class="k">if</span> <span class="o">[</span> <span class="nt">-n</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="nv">$PRETTIER_FULLY_STAGED</span><span class="s2">"</span> <span class="o">]</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="k">then
  </span>npx prettier <span class="nt">--write</span> <span class="nv">$PRETTIER_FULLY_STAGED</span>
  git add <span class="nv">$PRETTIER_FULLY_STAGED</span>
<span class="k">fi</span>

<span class="c"># Lint all staged files.</span>
<span class="k">if</span> <span class="o">[</span> <span class="nt">-n</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="nv">$PRETTIER_STAGED</span><span class="s2">"</span> <span class="o">]</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="k">then
  </span>npx prettier <span class="nt">--check</span> <span class="nv">$PRETTIER_STAGED</span>
<span class="k">fi</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<h3 id="ides">IDEs</h3>

<p>VS Code has excellent Prettier support. Use it. I personally prefer to default to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">editor.formatOnSave</code> turned on, and only disable it per project that doesn’t have Prettier.</p>

<h3 id="continuous-integration">Continuous integration</h3>

<p>We want to make sure we run <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">npm run lint:format</code> on CI. Simple as that. Worth mentioning <a href="https://pre-commit.ci/">pre-commit.ci</a>, compatible with the same pre-commit framework as above, which runs formatting on your behalf and commits the changes to PRs. I personally don’t use it, but it works.</p>

<p>A common gotcha when setting up Prettier in CI is if your builds are optimised to only run when specific folders are changed – by definition, the Prettier checks will have to run whenever any file supported by Prettier changes.</p>

<h2 id="documentation">Documentation</h2>

<p>Make sure your contributors are aware Prettier is in use, and that there is a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">npm run format</code> command available for cases where Prettier formatting doesn’t get automatically applied in an editor.</p>

<h2 id="git-blame-compatibility">Git blame compatibility</h2>

<p>GitHub makes it easy to skip a commit in the blame view. For git itself, we can use a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.git-blame-ignore-revs</code> file. <a href="https://github.com/prettier/prettier/blob/main/.git-blame-ignore-revs">Prettier itself</a> has an excellent example, which is self-documenting:</p>

<div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c"># git-blame ignored revisions</span>
<span class="c"># To configure, run</span>
<span class="c">#   git config blame.ignoreRevsFile .git-blame-ignore-revs</span>
<span class="c"># Requires Git &gt; 2.23</span>
<span class="c"># See https://git-scm.com/docs/git-blame#Documentation/git-blame.txt---ignore-revs-fileltfilegt</span>

<span class="c"># Prettier bump after release</span>
<span class="c"># 2.5.1</span>
4683a6284d53b913f129694a5be666fc55b06982
<span class="c"># 2.5.0</span>
846dbdd7e8c9deb315b3e663b3103c559e798a89
<span class="o">[</span>…]
</code></pre></div></div>

<h2 id="the-initial-reformatting">The initial reformatting</h2>

<p>All of the above steps should be done in the first PR, so they can easily be code reviewed. In the second PR, we can make the actual formatting changes. Run your <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">npm run format</code> now, and commit the results.</p>

<p>If your auto-formatting creates a lot of changes and you’ll want to review them manually – you could consider starting from a Prettier configuration that does fewer changes, commit the formatting, and add more changes gradually. This makes it easier to review different formatting changes overall.</p>

<h3 id="manual-issues-to-fix">Manual issues to fix</h3>

<p>If your project uses per-line linting disable comments, make sure the comments still target the correct lines after the reformatting. ESLint has an excellent <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">--report-unused-disable-directives</code> which helps a lot. Here’s an example where this happened:</p>

<div class="language-diff highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="gd">-  // eslint-disable-next-line func-names
</span>  $(
    '#new a.task-type-choice, #new a.choose-different-task-type',
    modal.body,
<span class="gd">-  ).on('click', function () {
</span><span class="gi">+  ).on('click', function onClickNew() {
</span></code></pre></div></div>

<p>There can be other compatibility issues with other static analysis tools, although that’s very rare. For example, I had to disable Prettier for a line where a Stylelint plugin wasn’t producing the expected output anymore – I’d suspect it’s the plugin’s analysis that’s causing the actual issue:</p>

<div class="language-diff highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="gd">-  --#{$name}: hsl(
-    #{var(--#{$name}-hue),
-    var(--#{$name}-saturation),
-    var(--#{$name}-lightness)}
-  );
</span><span class="gi">+  // Prettier causes a linting issue when reformatting this.
+  /* prettier-ignore */
+  --#{$name}: hsl(#{ var(--#{$name}-hue), var(--#{$name}-saturation), var(--#{$name}-lightness) });
</span></code></pre></div></div>

<p>I’ve never encountered a case where Prettier changed the semantics of the code at runtime, except perhaps for <a href="https://prettier.io/docs/en/options.html#trailing-commas">trailing commas in function parameters</a>, which should be watched out for on projects that support legacy browsers.</p>

<h2 id="after-the-reformatting">After the reformatting</h2>

<p>Merge it all, making sure CI is linting for Prettier formatting, and passes. Then edit your project’s <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.git-blame-ignore-revs</code> with the correct reformatting commit, and that’s it.</p>

<p>For projects with other contributors – make sure to let them know there will be conflicts, and how to resolve them. Here are instructions I made for Wagtail:</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="instructions-to-rebase-in-progress-prs">Instructions to rebase in-progress PRs</h2>

<p>Here are the high-level steps:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Rebase onto the commit before the reformatting (11ccf30f0044a326abef2a5c5568f373ffe46188, or can also be defined as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">af942a27e41b47e257b6cd46c01a13cd381fed04^1</code>, note the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">^1</code> suffix), with your usual rebasing methodology.</li>
  <li>Rebase onto the reformatting commit (af942a27e41b47e257b6cd46c01a13cd381fed04 / <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">af942a27e41b47e257b6cd46c01a13cd381fed04</code>), always favouring your branch’s changes, and auto-applying Prettier reformatting.</li>
  <li>Rebase onto <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">main</code> with your usual rebasing methodology.</li>
</ol>

<p>Here are step-by-step commands, tested on macOS with zsh:</p>

<div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c"># Make a copy of your branch</span>
git branch save/my-existing-branch my-existing-branch
<span class="c"># Make sure you have the latest `main` from Wagtail</span>
git remote add upstream git@github.com:wagtail/wagtail.git
git checkout main
git pull upstream main
<span class="c"># Rebase onto the commit preceding the reformatting to resolve conflicts that would have been present anyway.</span>
git checkout my-existing-branch
git rebase af942a27e41b47e257b6cd46c01a13cd381fed04^1
<span class="c"># Install Prettier and other Wagtail development dependencies</span>
<span class="c"># Make sure you use Node v16 and npm v8</span>
node <span class="nt">--version</span>
npm <span class="nt">--version</span>
npm <span class="nb">install</span>
<span class="c"># Test-run Prettier – this should show formatting errors.</span>
npm run lint:format
<span class="c"># Rebase again, this time with the reformatting as the base,</span>
<span class="c"># always preserving your changes in case of conflicts, and automatically reformatting with Prettier.</span>
git rebase <span class="nt">--strategy-option</span><span class="o">=</span>theirs <span class="nt">--exec</span> <span class="s1">'(npm run format || true) &amp;&amp; git add . &amp;&amp; git commit --amend --no-edit --no-verify'</span> af942a27e41b47e257b6cd46c01a13cd381fed04
<span class="c"># Test-run Prettier – this should show no formatting errors.</span>
npm run lint:format
<span class="c"># Finally rebase onto the latest version from Wagtail main, as per usual.</span>
git rebase main
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>That’s it! There’s a small chance (see below) there may be conflicts with our linters, requiring further manual intervention. Run a final <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">npm run lint</code> if you want to be sure.</p>

<p>There are a few things worth noting:</p>

<h3 id="its-a-bit-slow">It’s a bit slow</h3>

<p>This will reformat the whole project for every commit to be rebased, so it’s slow for PRs with lots of commits. It’d have been possible for us to only reformat the files changed by a given commit, but I was having trouble doing this in a cross-shell-compatible way.</p>

<h3 id="cases-where-manual-changes-will-be-needed">Cases where manual changes will be needed</h3>

<p>Once this is applied, there is still a risk there’ll be code that clashes with Prettier reformatting, which will need manual intervention. See for example <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail/commit/37026d521f818bab3724c74df93e9e690e93a9d5">37026d521f818bab3724c74df93e9e690e93a9d5</a>. I would expect this to be rare. As part of our main refactoring, there were two kinds of issues:</p>

<ul>
  <li>1 conflict with Stylelint, where Prettier splitting a long expression into multiple lines changes how the expression is interpreted by our linting.</li>
  <li>8 conflicts with ESLint, where Prettier moved <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">eslint-disable</code> comments in places where they no longer applied to the correct line.</li>
</ul>

<p>If in doubt, run <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">npm run lint</code> to check for any issues of this nature.</p>

<h2 id="git-blame">git blame</h2>

<p>For people who use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">git blame</code>, we have introduced a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.git-blame-ignore-revs</code> which allows you to ignore the reformatting. See <a href="https://git-scm.com/docs/git-blame#Documentation/git-blame.txt---ignore-revs-fileltfilegt">the official documentation</a> and the file in question for further information.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wagtail developer jobs: where to look]]></title>
    <link href="https://thib.me/wagtail-developer-jobs-where-to-look"/>
    <updated>2022-01-13T06:21:09+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://thib.me/wagtail-developer-jobs-where-to-look</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Looking for a Wagtail job? Or to hire a developer? Here are good places to check.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>There are more options than you might think! Wagtail being based on Django, anyone with a Django skillset will be productive with Wagtail. As such, this list is equally relevant when searching for or advertising Django developer jobs.</p>

<h2 id="chat">Chat</h2>

<p>This is my favourite option by far, with the #jobs channel in the <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail/wiki/Slack">Wagtail Slack</a>. Our Slack workspace is very active, with #jobs being one of the most viewed channels. Using chat also makes it much simpler for people to have a conversation about a given job offer.</p>

<p>Here is a screenshot of the workspace’s statistics, showing 250 weekly active users:</p>

<p><a href="/images/blog/wagtail-developer-jobs-where-to-look/wagtailcms-stats-slack.png"><img src="/images/blog/wagtail-developer-jobs-where-to-look/wagtailcms-stats-slack.png" alt="Line chart of Weekly active members and messages posted, over December 2021 and January 2022. For Monday 10/01, there were 247 active members and 55 who posted messages" /></a></p>

<h2 id="newsletters">Newsletters</h2>

<p>This is a good option but the lead time is high, as there are only a few ad placements available per week.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://django-news.com/">Django News</a> – regularly includes Wagtail content.</li>
  <li><a href="https://pycoders.com/">PyCoder’s Weekly</a> – occasional mentions of Wagtail.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="conferences">Conferences</h2>

<p>There are a lot of great options here, with a good number of events recurring every year.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.wagtail.space/">Wagtail Space</a>, and <a href="https://us.wagtail.space/">Wagtail Space US</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://2021.djangocon.eu/">DjangoCon Europe</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://djangocon.us/">DjangoCon US</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://2022.pythonwebconf.com/">Python Web Conference</a> (coming up soon!)</li>
  <li><a href="https://djangoday.dk/">Django Day Copenhagen</a> (also coming up soon)</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="job-listings">Job listings</h2>

<p>General-purpose job sites are always worth looking at for job offers matching “Wagtail” or “Django”. There are also a few specialised job boards:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.djangoproject.com/community/jobs/">Django jobs RSS</a>, aggregating other job boards.</li>
  <li><a href="https://djangojobs.net/">https://djangojobs.net/</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://djangogigs.com/">https://djangogigs.com/</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wagtail-developers">Wagtail developers</h2>

<p>Last but not least, <a href="https://madewithwagtail.org/developers/">Made with Wagtail developer profiles</a> list 200+ organisations that create Wagtail sites, some of which likely will be hiring. The profiles are ordered by number of Wagtail sites published, which helps getting a sense of the size of an organisation’s Wagtail practice.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[aria-invalid="true" with aria-describedby]]></title>
    <link href="https://thib.me/aria-invalid-true-with-aria-describedby"/>
    <updated>2022-01-12T22:42:03+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://thib.me/aria-invalid-true-with-aria-describedby</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As part of Django’s <a href="https://github.com/django/deps/blob/main/accepted/0011-accessibility-team.rst">accessibility team</a>, I’ve been doing a lot of research into specific patterns. Today – <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">aria-required="true"</code> combined with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">aria-describedby</code> for error messages! Is it good? Is it redundant? What do authorative sources say?</p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>This is a copy of my <a href="https://github.com/django/django/pull/15036#issuecomment-1008738687">GitHub comment on django/django#15036</a> to keep for future reference</em>.</p>

<h2 id="tldr">TL;DR;</h2>

<p>TL;DR; “<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">aria-invalid ="true"</code> + <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">aria-describedby</code> pointing at error message” seems to me like it would be the best for Django. It’s recommended in the non-normative <a href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/WCAG21/Techniques/aria/ARIA21">ARIA21</a> technique, and by a renowned expert in the field. I found one pattern that seems better than it in some cases, but I don’t think it’s as good of a fit for Django.</p>

<h2 id="recommendations-for-the-pattern">Recommendations for the pattern</h2>

<p>I could find the following sources recommending <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">aria-invalid="true"</code> usage alongside <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">aria-describedby</code>:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The official (non-normative) <a href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/WCAG21/Techniques/aria/ARIA21">ARIA21 Using Aria-Invalid to Indicate An Error Field</a> technique from WCAG:</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>When visible text is used to programmatically identify a failed field and / or convey how the error can be corrected, setting aria-invalid to “true” is not required from a strict compliance standpoint but may still provide helpful information for users.</p>
</blockquote>

<ul>
  <li>A <a href="https://web-a11y.slack.com/archives/C042TSFGN/p1557348802029700">post from Léonie Watson on the web-a11y Slack</a>:</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>[…]
Or you can use aria-describedby to make the association, like this:
[…] &gt; <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;input type="text" id="this" aria-describedby="error" ...&gt;</code> &gt; […] &gt; <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;p id="error"&gt;Don't forget to enter your first name!&lt;/p&gt;</code></p>

  <p>You can also use aria-invalid=”true” on the input, as you have done, for belt and braces information.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Those two sources indicate <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">aria-describedby</code> pointing at the error message could be sufficient. Using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">aria-invalid="true"</code> basically just helps unambiguously identifying fields that are in error, rather than relying on the wording of the error messages conveyed via <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">aria-describedby</code> only.</p>

<h2 id="alternative">Alternative</h2>

<p>I couldn’t find anyone actively recommending against this combination, however the GOV.UK design system <a href="https://github.com/alphagov/govuk-frontend/issues/1168">decided not to use it</a>. They instead added an <a href="https://design-system.service.gov.uk/components/error-message/#label">“Error:” prefix for all error messages</a>, as visually hidden / screen-reader-only text:</p>

<div class="language-html highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>[…]
<span class="nt">&lt;p</span> <span class="na">id=</span><span class="s">"national-insurance-number-error"</span> <span class="na">class=</span><span class="s">"govuk-error-message"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;span</span> <span class="na">class=</span><span class="s">"govuk-visually-hidden"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>Error:<span class="nt">&lt;/span&gt;</span> Enter a National Insurance
  number in the correct format
<span class="nt">&lt;/p&gt;</span>
<span class="nt">&lt;input</span>
  <span class="na">class=</span><span class="s">"govuk-input govuk-input--error"</span>
  <span class="na">id=</span><span class="s">"national-insurance-number"</span>
  <span class="na">name=</span><span class="s">"national-insurance-number"</span>
  <span class="na">type=</span><span class="s">"text"</span>
  <span class="na">aria-describedby=</span><span class="s">"national-insurance-number-hint national-insurance-number-error"</span>
<span class="nt">/&gt;</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>I can see some clear advantages to this:</p>

<ul>
  <li>It’s equally as unambiguous for screen reader users that the fields are in error (compare Django’s <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">This field is required.</code> message or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Enter a whole number.</code> with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Error: This field is required.</code> or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Error: Enter a whole number.</code>).</li>
  <li>“Error:” is more plain language than “Invalid entry”</li>
  <li>Since this doesn’t rely on ARIA, screen reader support for this is better than <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">aria-invalid="true"</code></li>
</ul>

<p>I can also see some issues:</p>

<ul>
  <li>It’s more opinionated markup to maintain / less “by-the-book semantic HTML”</li>
  <li>Django’s error messages are meant to be customized with no oversight on how implementers will ultimately word them, so adding a prefix wouldn’t always be appropriate.</li>
  <li>It’s one more string that will need translations (not necessarily a big deal for such a generic word but does constraint the languages with which Django’s forms rendering could be used).</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="recommendation-for-django">Recommendation for Django</h2>

<p>Based on this, for Django, I’d still recommend <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">aria-invalid="true"</code> wherever possible, and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">aria-describedby</code> for the error message wherever possible. So both together, wherever possible. It’s a more established pattern than bespoke error message prefixes, and lower maintenance. <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">aria-invalid="true"</code> support isn’t as good, but good enough for something that’s used <em>in addition to</em> <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">aria-describedby</code>.</p>

<h2 id="caveats">Caveats</h2>

<ul>
  <li>This is based on <a href="https://a11ysupport.io/">a11ysupport.io</a> data, which only tested support on <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;input type="text"&gt;</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;select&gt;</code>.</li>
  <li>I only looked at <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">aria-invalid="true"</code>. There are other <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">aria-invalid</code> values, which are harder to use and I wouldn’t recommend at this time.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<p>Further references:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://a11ysupport.io/tech/aria/aria-invalid_attribute">a11ysupport.io support data for aria-invalid</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://a11ysupport.io/tech/aria/aria-describedby_attribute">a11ysupport.io support data for aria-describedby</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.powermapper.com/tests/screen-readers/aria/">PowerMapper support data for aria-describedby</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2022 web conferences]]></title>
    <link href="https://thib.me/2022-web-conferences"/>
    <updated>2022-01-08T17:42:03+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://thib.me/2022-web-conferences</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here is a small list of conferences I put together for 2022, as I was looking for speaking opportunities, with a particular focus on Europe and America. Hope this helps!</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="uk-govcamp-2022">UK GovCamp 2022</h2>

<p>20th-22nd January 2022. Unconference, CFP on the day.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.ukgovcamp.com/2021/11/13/announcing-ukgovcamp-2022/">https://www.ukgovcamp.com/2021/11/13/announcing-ukgovcamp-2022/</a></p>

<h2 id="djangoday-cph-2021-2022">DjangoDay CPH 2021 2022</h2>

<p>April/May 2022. No CFP currently.</p>

<p><a href="https://2021.djangoday.dk/">https://2021.djangoday.dk/</a></p>

<h2 id="pycon-us-2022">PyCon US 2022</h2>

<p>April 27, 2022 - May 3, 2022. Salt Lake City. CFP already closed.</p>

<p><a href="https://us.pycon.org/2022/">https://us.pycon.org/2022/</a></p>

<h2 id="wagtail-space-us-2022">Wagtail Space US 2022</h2>

<p>March 24-26 2022. Cleveland. CFP online, no end date stated.</p>

<p><a href="https://us.wagtail.space/">https://us.wagtail.space/</a></p>

<h2 id="cityjs-london">CityJS London</h2>

<p>March 23-25th 2022. London. CFP online, ending 15/01/2022</p>

<p><a href="https://cityjsconf.org/speakers">https://cityjsconf.org/speakers</a></p>

<h2 id="python-web-conf">Python Web Conf</h2>

<p>March 21 - 25 2022. Online. No CFP.</p>

<p><a href="https://2022.pythonwebconf.com/">https://2022.pythonwebconf.com/</a></p>

<h2 id="web-directions-hover">Web Directions Hover</h2>

<p>April 1 &amp; 8. Focussed on CSS, in March 2022, CFP closes Dec 31 2021</p>

<p><a href="https://webdirections.org/speaking/">https://webdirections.org/speaking/</a></p>

<h2 id="mixit-2022">MiXiT 2022</h2>

<p>May 24th 25th, 2022, Lyon, France. CFP deadline: 02/02/2022 <a href="https://www.papercall.io/mixit2022">https://www.papercall.io/mixit2022</a></p>

<p><a href="https://mixitconf.org/en/">https://mixitconf.org/en/</a></p>

<h2 id="web-directions-lazy-load">Web Directions Lazy Load</h2>

<p>May 20 &amp; 27. Focussed on front end performance in May 2022, CFP closes Jan 31 2022</p>

<p><a href="https://webdirections.org/speaking/">https://webdirections.org/speaking/</a></p>

<h2 id="pycon-italy-2022">PyCon Italy 2022</h2>

<p>2-5 June 2022. Florence. CFP deadline: 09/01/2022</p>

<p><a href="https://pycon.it/en">https://pycon.it/en</a></p>

<h2 id="jsconf-budapest-2021-2022">JSConf Budapest 2021 2022</h2>

<p>2-3 June 2022, Budapest. No CFP currently.</p>

<p><a href="https://jsconfbp.com/">https://jsconfbp.com/</a></p>

<h2 id="pixel-pioneers-2020-2022">Pixel Pioneers 2020 2022</h2>

<p>10 June 2022, Bristol. No CFP.</p>

<p><a href="https://pixelpioneers.co/">https://pixelpioneers.co/</a></p>

<h2 id="halfstack-newquay-2022">HalfStack Newquay 2022</h2>

<p>Friday 1st July 2022, Newquay (/ˈnjuːki/) (UK). CFP under way, no deadline.</p>

<p>Creative JavaScript and web development.</p>

<p><a href="https://halfstackconf.com/newquay/">https://halfstackconf.com/newquay/</a></p>

<h2 id="web-directions-global-scope">Web Directions Global Scope</h2>

<p>July 1 &amp; 8. Focused exclusively on JavaScript, in June 2022, CFP closes March 31st 2022</p>

<p><a href="https://webdirections.org/speaking/">https://webdirections.org/speaking/</a></p>

<h2 id="halfstack-new-york-2022">HalfStack New York 2022</h2>

<p>August 2022, New York. CFP under way, no deadline.</p>

<p>Creative JavaScript and web development.</p>

<p><a href="https://halfstackconf.com/newyork/">https://halfstackconf.com/newyork/</a></p>

<h2 id="web-directions-code">Web Directions Code</h2>

<p>September 2 &amp; 9 Focussed on the Web Platform and PWAs in September 2022, CFP closes May 30 2022</p>

<p><a href="https://webdirections.org/speaking/">https://webdirections.org/speaking/</a></p>

<h2 id="halfstack-london-2021-2022">HalfStack London 2021 2022</h2>

<p>Friday 23rd September 2022, London. CFP under way, no deadline.</p>

<p>Creative JavaScript and web development.</p>

<p><a href="https://halfstackconf.com/london/">https://halfstackconf.com/london/</a></p>

<h2 id="nordic-js-2022">Nordic JS 2022</h2>

<p>6-7 October 2022, Stockholm. CFP under way (ish?), no deadline.</p>

<p><a href="https://nordicjs.com/call-for-speakers">https://nordicjs.com/call-for-speakers</a></p>

<h2 id="web-directions-aaa">Web Directions AAA</h2>

<p>October 21 &amp; 28. Focussed on accessibility for front end developers in October 2022, CFP closes June 30 2022</p>

<p><a href="https://webdirections.org/speaking/">https://webdirections.org/speaking/</a></p>

<h2 id="canux-2022">CanUX 2022</h2>

<p>3-6 Nov 2022, Ottawa, Canada. No CFP announced yet</p>

<p><a href="https://canux.io/">https://canux.io/</a></p>

<h2 id="ffconf-2022">ffconf 2022</h2>

<p>Friday 11 Nov 2022. Brighton. No CFP announced yet</p>

<p><a href="https://ffconf.org/">https://ffconf.org/</a></p>

<h2 id="web-directions-code-leaders">Web Directions Code Leaders</h2>

<p>November 30 2022 Code Leaders is a one day focussed engineering leadership conference taking place the day before our Summit. CFPs close July 31.</p>

<p><a href="https://webdirections.org/speaking/">https://webdirections.org/speaking/</a></p>

<h2 id="web-directions-summit">Web Directions Summit</h2>

<p>December 1 &amp; 2. Web Directions Summit takes place in early December in Sydney, and features several tracks–front end engineering, design and product management. CFPs close June 30 2022</p>

<p><a href="https://webdirections.org/speaking/">https://webdirections.org/speaking/</a></p>

<h2 id="web-directions-safe">Web Directions Safe</h2>

<p>Dec. 9 &amp; 16 2022. Focussed on privacy, security and identity for front end developers in December 2022, CFP closes July 31 2022</p>

<p><a href="https://webdirections.org/speaking/">https://webdirections.org/speaking/</a></p>

<h2 id="halfstack-phoenix-2022---2023">HalfStack Phoenix 2022 - 2023</h2>

<p>2022 - 2023, Phoenix. CFP under way, ending 15/09/2021.</p>

<p>Creative JavaScript and web development.</p>

<p><a href="https://halfstackconf.com/phoenix/">https://halfstackconf.com/phoenix/</a></p>

<h2 id="halfstack-vienna-2022">HalfStack Vienna 2022</h2>

<p>2022 - 2023, Vienna. CFP under way, no deadline.</p>

<p>Creative JavaScript and web development.</p>

<p><a href="https://halfstackconf.com/vienna/">https://halfstackconf.com/vienna/</a></p>

<h2 id="djangocon-us-2022">DjangoCon US 2022</h2>

<p>No announcement yet. Expected: San Diego fall 2022.</p>

<h2 id="pycon-uk-2020-2021-2022">PyCon UK 2020 2021 2022?</h2>

<p>No date announced except for “2021”. Cardiff. No CFP announced yet.</p>

<p><a href="https://2020.pyconuk.org/">https://2020.pyconuk.org/</a></p>

<h2 id="djangocon-eu-2022">DjangoCon EU 2022</h2>

<p>No plans as of yet</p>

<h2 id="jamstack-2022">Jamstack 2022</h2>

<p>No plans as of yet</p>

<p><a href="https://jamstackconf.com/">https://jamstackconf.com/</a></p>

<h2 id="pycon-lithuania-2022">PyCon Lithuania 2022</h2>

<p>No plans as of yet</p>

<p><a href="https://www.pycon.lt/">https://www.pycon.lt/</a></p>

<h2 id="webrebels-2020-2021-2022">WebRebels 2020 2021 2022</h2>

<p>No plans as of yet</p>

<p><a href="https://www.webrebels.org/">https://www.webrebels.org/</a></p>

<h2 id="europython-2022">EuroPython 2022</h2>

<p>No plans as of yet</p>

<p><a href="https://ep2021.europython.eu/">https://ep2021.europython.eu/</a></p>

<h2 id="other-lists">Other lists</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://confs.tech/">https://confs.tech/</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://frontendfront.com/conferences/">https://frontendfront.com/conferences/</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DjangoCon US 2021: Kontrasto – improving accessibility with Python]]></title>
    <link href="https://thib.me/djangocon-us-2021-kontrasto-improving-accessibility-with-python"/>
    <updated>2021-10-22T09:01:32+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://thib.me/djangocon-us-2021-kontrasto-improving-accessibility-with-python</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Slides for my <a href="https://2021.djangocon.us/talks/kontrasto-improving-accessibility-with/">DjangoCon US 2021 talk</a> on <a href="https://kontrasto.netlify.app/">Kontrasto</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/10718N6sEdx37JqMrBaS4prVOs-kH9ad61lsRTzdNPmI/edit">Google Slides: DjangoCon US 2021 - Kontrasto: improving accessibility with Python</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1L6UZbN8VdTX_i6yTKghwB-5FalCA05s8/view?usp=sharing">PDF export</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1cwVsGcikJxG_K0Sy98WY5J6ajZXENoIP/view?usp=sharing">Plain-text transcript</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[WCAG 2.2: new accessibility guidelines on the way]]></title>
    <link href="https://thib.me/wcag-22-accessibility-guidelines"/>
    <updated>2021-08-13T16:52:22+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://thib.me/wcag-22-accessibility-guidelines</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In web accessibility testing, WCAG 2.1 is the gold standard. But talk to experts – and they’ll be quick to tell you it’s a very low baseline. WCAG 2.2’s latest draft introduces new criteria, relevant for all websites.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="whats-new-in-wcag-22">What’s new in WCAG 2.2</h2>

<p>Plenty of good things – there are 9 new success criteria:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Guideline 2.4 Navigable
    <ul>
      <li><a href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/standards-guidelines/wcag/new-in-22/#2411-focus-appearance-minimum-aa">2.4.11 Focus Appearance (Minimum) (AA)</a></li>
      <li><a href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/standards-guidelines/wcag/new-in-22/#2412-focus-appearance-enhanced-aaa">2.4.12 Focus Appearance (Enhanced) (AAA)</a></li>
      <li><a href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/standards-guidelines/wcag/new-in-22/#2413-page-break-navigation-a">2.4.13 Page Break Navigation (A)</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Guideline 2.5 Input Modalities
    <ul>
      <li><a href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/standards-guidelines/wcag/new-in-22/#257-dragging-movements-aa">2.5.7 Dragging Movements (AA)</a></li>
      <li><a href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/standards-guidelines/wcag/new-in-22/#258-target-size-minimum-aa">2.5.8 Target Size (Minimum) (AA)</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Guideline 3.2 Predictable
    <ul>
      <li><a href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/standards-guidelines/wcag/new-in-22/#326-consistent-help-a">3.2.6 Consistent Help (A)</a></li>
      <li><a href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/standards-guidelines/wcag/new-in-22/#327-visible-controls-aa">3.2.7 Visible Controls (AA)</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Guideline 3.3 Input Assistance
    <ul>
      <li><a href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/standards-guidelines/wcag/new-in-22/#337-accessible-authentication-a">3.3.7 Accessible Authentication (A)</a></li>
      <li><a href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/standards-guidelines/wcag/new-in-22/#338-redundant-entry-a">3.3.8 Redundant Entry (A)</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>As well as the normative guidelines, all criteria also use <a href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/people-use-web/user-stories/">stories of web users</a> to better convey what problems we are trying to prevent with those guidelines – and what “success” looks like.</p>

<p>There are a lot of good resources covering the new criteria in much better detail than we ever could – we’d highly recommend taking a look at Alastair Campbell’s talk <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EZlqSwgKuZE">WCAG 2.2: What’s new and what to do with it</a> at the Virtua11y conference.</p>

<h2 id="applying-wcag-22-to-sites">Applying WCAG 2.2 to sites</h2>

<p>There won’t be any legal requirements to follow this new draft version for quite a while. That said, the new guidelines are so good they are well worth implementing and testing for right away.</p>

<p>WCAG 2.1 is a good baseline, but there are a lot of areas where it falls short and we should aim beyond. To illustrate – here is a color contrast fail, generated with <a href="https://whocanuse.com/">Who Can Use</a>. According to WCAG 2.1 rules, the black text would be higher-contrast over this shade of blue than white text:</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/wcag-22-accessibility-guidelines/whocanuse-blue.png" alt="Comparison of lorem copy in white and black, over a blue background (hex code #2E7CD6). White has a contrast ratio of 4.23:1, non-compliant, black has 4.97:1, passing level AA." /></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Comparison of lorem copy in white and black, over a blue background (hex code #2E7CD6). White has a contrast ratio of 4.23:1, non-compliant, black has 4.97:1, passing level AA</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is due to how basic the contrast calculations are in WCAG 2.1. This specific issue will – hopefully – be addressed in the upcoming <a href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/standards-guidelines/wcag/wcag3-intro/">WCAG 3.0</a>. It’s still a very early draft, but is well worth being aware of as well if you’re critically thinking of where else WCAG 2.1 might be falling short.</p>

<h2 id="we-can-help">We can help</h2>

<p>Torchbox offers standalone <a href="https://torchbox.com/digital-products/accessibility-testing/">accessibility consulting services</a>, with the goal of helping organisations aim beyond compliance. Don’t hesitate to get in touch if you want your site to get ahead of the curve.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DjangoCon Europe 2021 sprints – Accessibility review of PyCon Lithuania]]></title>
    <link href="https://thib.me/djangocon-europe-2021-sprints-accessibility-review-pycon-lithuania"/>
    <updated>2021-06-07T18:21:03+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://thib.me/djangocon-europe-2021-sprints-accessibility-review-pycon-lithuania</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here are the results of an accessibility audit I did for the <a href="https://github.com/PyConLT/pyconlt.github.io/pull/12">PyCon Lithuania website</a>, as part of the DjangoCon Europe 2021 sprints. I recorded myself going through this and put it up on YouTube, so we have a demo for each of the issues: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NH4VWUguxUw">DjangoCon Europe 2021 sprints – Accessibility review of PyCon Lithuania’s website</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->

<iframe title="DjangoCon Europe 2021 sprints – Accessibility review of PyCon Lithuania’s website" width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/NH4VWUguxUw" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>I think the most problematic issue was with the animating banner on Safari, which made it completely impossible to navigate the page with a screen reader. Other than this, most issues were relatively minor.</p>

<p>The main issues I didn’t get to are the ones with buttons / links – the fact having disabled buttons is confusing, and that there are lots of contrast issues with those disabled styles. The focus styles also have poor contrast for the buttons that are focusable.</p>

<p>My recommended fix for these would be to completely remove any button that’s currently disabled from the page, so there is no confusion.</p>

<p>Sections:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NH4VWUguxUw&amp;t=0s">00:00</a> Intro</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NH4VWUguxUw&amp;t=40s">00:40</a> Audit methodology</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NH4VWUguxUw&amp;t=109s">01:49</a> HTML5 validation</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NH4VWUguxUw&amp;t=260s">04:20</a> Reviewing HTML templates</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NH4VWUguxUw&amp;t=780s">13:00</a> Alt text for photos</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NH4VWUguxUw&amp;t=1190s">19:50</a> Accessibility Insights automated checks</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NH4VWUguxUw&amp;t=1290s">21:30</a> Checking landmarks</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NH4VWUguxUw&amp;t=1380s">23:00</a> Color contrast checks</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NH4VWUguxUw&amp;t=1515s">25:15</a> Checking headings</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NH4VWUguxUw&amp;t=1605s">26:45</a> Using h123 for the document outline</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NH4VWUguxUw&amp;t=1665s">27:45</a> Tab stops</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NH4VWUguxUw&amp;t=1778s">29:38</a> Mobile support</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NH4VWUguxUw&amp;t=1900s">31:40</a> Looping animations</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NH4VWUguxUw&amp;t=1960s">32:40</a> Testing with VoiceOver in Safari</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NH4VWUguxUw&amp;t=2160s">36:00</a> Performance issues with banner animation</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DjangoCon Europe 2021 sprints – Accessibility review of Django Postgres Metrics]]></title>
    <link href="https://thib.me/djangocon-europe-2021-sprints-accessibility-review-django-postgres-metrics"/>
    <updated>2021-06-05T21:07:49+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://thib.me/djangocon-europe-2021-sprints-accessibility-review-django-postgres-metrics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here are the results of an accessibility audit I did for <a href="https://github.com/django-postgres-metrics/django-postgres-metrics/issues/57">Django Postgres Metrics</a>, as part of the DjangoCon Europe 2021 sprints. I recorded myself going through this and put it up on YouTube, so we have a demo for each of the issues: <a href="https://youtu.be/8pegTdRaUDg">DjangoCon Europe 2021 sprints – Accessibility review of Django Postgres Metrics</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->

<iframe title="DjangoCon Europe 2021 sprints – Accessibility review of Django Postgres Metrics" width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/8pegTdRaUDg" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="tldr-011515">TL;DR; <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8pegTdRaUDg&amp;t=4515s">01:15:15</a></h2>

<p>TL;DR; in video form: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8pegTdRaUDg&amp;t=4515s">01:15:15</a></p>

<ul>
  <li>Most issues come from Django for the UI, and the RTD theme for the documentation</li>
  <li>Great effort on translations and RTL support! It’s wonderful to see this being done as a baseline</li>
  <li>Very semantic tables markup, which definitely matters for the metrics’ display</li>
  <li>Some issues from this package with dark mode support, which make the library potentially unusable for dark mode users. Fixed in <a href="https://github.com/django-postgres-metrics/django-postgres-metrics/pull/59">#59</a>.</li>
  <li>There are a few improvements for screen reader users to be done here and there</li>
  <li>Table sorting was particularly hard to follow with a screen reader, although I suspect this is the Django implementation</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="about-the-audit-000105">About the audit <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8pegTdRaUDg&amp;t=65s">00:01:05</a></h2>

<p>Scope:</p>

<ul>
  <li>HTML templates in GitHub</li>
  <li>UI in the Django admin (minimal customisations)</li>
  <li>Documentation in README</li>
  <li>Documentation in Read the Docs (default sphinx-rtd theme)</li>
</ul>

<p>Methodology:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Automated tests with Accessibility Insights with Chrome</li>
  <li>Keyboard navigation (tab stops)</li>
  <li>Color contrast</li>
  <li>Dark mode support</li>
  <li>RTL support</li>
  <li>Mobile support</li>
  <li>Screen reader navigation (VoiceOver in Safari)</li>
  <li>Other things picked up along the way</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="html-templates-000222">HTML templates <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8pegTdRaUDg&amp;t=142s">00:02:22</a></h2>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">index.html</code>:</p>

<ul>
  <li>There are a lot of links with the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">title</code> attribute being used in. This can be announced multiple times by some screen readers, so I would suggest not using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">title</code> wherever it matches the visible label of the link</li>
  <li>Table markup for the navigation in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">index.html</code> looks great, however this would be much quicker to navigate with a screen reader by using simpler markup, for example <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ul</code> with a list item for each link.</li>
</ul>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">table.html</code>:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Place the breadcrumb in a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;nav aria-label="Breadcrumbs"&gt;&lt;/nav&gt;</code> landmark, so screen reader users can bypass it or reach it more easily</li>
  <li>Add <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">aria-current="page"</code> to the current page so it’s announced as such. Fixed in <a href="https://github.com/django-postgres-metrics/django-postgres-metrics/pull/58">#58</a>.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="ui-000738">UI <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8pegTdRaUDg&amp;t=458s">00:07:38</a></h2>

<h3 id="automated-tests-with-accessibility-insights-with-chrome">Automated tests with Accessibility Insights with Chrome</h3>

<ul>
  <li>A lot of color contrast issues, but I believe they all come from Django itself</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="keyboard-navigation-001235">Keyboard navigation <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8pegTdRaUDg&amp;t=755s">00:12:35</a></h3>

<ul>
  <li>Missing a skip link on all pages – Django issue</li>
  <li>On metric pages, I found it a bit odd how the tab focus moves from the breadcrumb, to the package’s nav to the right, and then back to the metrics on the left. It’d be better to go straight from breadcrumb to the metrics’ tables.</li>
  <li>Likely a Django issue – the tab order for sorting is unexpected (right-to-left)</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="color-contrast">Color contrast</h3>

<ul>
  <li>In the package’s views in the “POSTGRESQL METRICS” nav, there isn’t enough contrast between the “active” menu item and the other ones, so people won’t be able to tell which menu item is active. This is both for the text, and the “selected” indicator”. I would suggest adding an underline to the text. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8pegTdRaUDg&amp;t=1584s">00:26:24</a></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="dark-mode-001603">Dark mode <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8pegTdRaUDg&amp;t=963s">00:16:03</a></h3>

<ul>
  <li>None of the package’s <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ok</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">warning</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">critical</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">info</code> states work in dark mode. They make the table’s contents completely unreadable. A solution would be to use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">@media (prefers-color-scheme: dark)</code> styles like Django does, however I would recommend another approach that doesn’t rely on background color as the color also won’t be picked up by blind users – it’d be better to represent those 4 states with an icon, that could then have a text alternative, or just a label. Fixed in <a href="https://github.com/django-postgres-metrics/django-postgres-metrics/pull/59">#59</a>.</li>
</ul>

<p>Illustration:</p>

<p><a href="/images/blog/djangocon-europe-2021-sprints-accessibility-review-django-postgres-metrics/django-postgres-metrics-dark-mode.png"><img src="/images/blog/djangocon-europe-2021-sprints-accessibility-review-django-postgres-metrics/django-postgres-metrics-dark-mode.png" alt="Screenshot of four highlighted rows in Django Postgres Metrics in dark mode. The rows aren’t readable" /></a></p>

<h3 id="rtl-support-001920">RTL support <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8pegTdRaUDg&amp;t=1160s">00:19:20</a></h3>

<p>😐 I did all of my testing without having configured the language in Django settings, forgetting Django uses this to set <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">LANGUAGE_BIDI</code> and load the correct stylesheet. As far as I can tell there are no issues here!</p>

<h3 id="mobile-support-002415">Mobile support <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8pegTdRaUDg&amp;t=1455s">00:24:15</a></h3>

<p>(this is more “small browser” support really, I didn’t do any touch navigation testing)</p>

<ul>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">urlize</code>d links cause the page to overflow and scroll in 2 directions at once. That’s bad. For this, and for screen readers, I’d recommend using proper link labels.</li>
  <li>Tables also cause the page to overflow and scroll in 2 directions. It would be better if they overflowed the page but the overflow was scrollable for the table separately (wrap the table in a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;div&gt;</code> with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">overflow: scroll</code>).</li>
  <li>With the way tables resize currently, they cause some of the cells with long values to reflow, which makes big numbers harder to read in my opinion. Scroll would be better in this instance.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="screen-reader-navigation-voiceover-with-safari-003000">Screen reader navigation (VoiceOver with Safari) <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8pegTdRaUDg&amp;t=1800s">00:30:00</a></h3>

<p>Dashboard:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Django issue – the views should be using ARIA landmarks to facilitate navigation.</li>
  <li>Prefer displaying “POSTGRESQL METRICS” in TitleCase or lowercase as much as possible, rather than uppercase, as TTS is prone to mispronounce PostgreSQL if it’s all uppercase.</li>
  <li>The “show” link need a more descriptive label for screen reader users (with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">aria-label</code>) so they can be understood without the visual context the links are in on the page. Alternatively, remove those links, as they do the same thing as the link next to them that has a better label already. Fixed in <a href="https://github.com/django-postgres-metrics/django-postgres-metrics/pull/58">#58</a>.</li>
  <li>Django issue – duplicate h1 heading</li>
</ul>

<p>Metrics views:</p>

<ul>
  <li>All of the custom views are missing a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;title&gt;</code> matching the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;h1&gt;</code> <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8pegTdRaUDg&amp;t=915s">00:15:15</a>. Fixed in <a href="https://github.com/django-postgres-metrics/django-postgres-metrics/pull/58">#58</a>.</li>
  <li>Prefer to use links with human-friendly labels over <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">urlize</code> URLs. These don’t announce very well with screen reader text-to-speech unless the user knows how to navigate word-by-word or character-by-character <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8pegTdRaUDg&amp;t=678s">00:11:18</a></li>
  <li>Django issue (?) I found the table ordering to be very confusing</li>
  <li>Consider adding spaces around <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">=</code> signs in table captions so screen readers TTS have a better chance of pronouncing the text correctly</li>
  <li>Currently the warning/info/ok/critical status are invisible for screen reader users. I’d suggesting adding a screen-reader only label, or an icon + label</li>
  <li>Some of the larger numbers in the tables are pronounced as identifiers (“one three five”) rather than numbers (“one hundred thirty five”). Consider adding numeric separators to make numbers more readable for humans and text-to-speech.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="other-things-picked-up-along-the-way">Other things picked up along the way</h3>

<ul>
  <li>The bigger values in tables are picked up by my browser as telephone numbers. This might warrant a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;meta name="format-detection" content="telephone=no"/&gt;</code>.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="docs-in-readme-005315">Docs in README <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8pegTdRaUDg&amp;t=3195s">00:53:15</a></h2>

<ul>
  <li>The project’s name <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">django-postgres-metrics</code> is being read letter-by-letter by VoiceOver, unless I manually switch to word-by-word navigation. In the main heading, I would suggest switching to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Django Postgres Metrics</code> to make it more likely for people to understand what the project is.</li>
  <li>The badges’ alt text should match the text on the images. This is likely impossible, but I’d suggest changing alt text to match the visible text more closely. Fixed in <a href="https://github.com/django-postgres-metrics/django-postgres-metrics/pull/58">#58</a>.</li>
  <li>Python and Django versions badges should link to some place those versions are available in text format (or add the versions hard-coded in the alt text). Fixed in <a href="https://github.com/django-postgres-metrics/django-postgres-metrics/pull/58">#58</a>.</li>
  <li>It would be nice to use more descriptive alt text for the screenshot. Fixed in <a href="https://github.com/django-postgres-metrics/django-postgres-metrics/pull/58">#58</a>.</li>
  <li>The “AT” and “DOT” in the email address are read as acronyms. Would be nice to replace with lowercase variants so they are read as words. Fixed in <a href="https://github.com/django-postgres-metrics/django-postgres-metrics/pull/58">#58</a>.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="documentation-in-read-the-docs-default-sphinx-rtd-theme-010045">Documentation in Read the Docs (default sphinx-rtd theme) <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8pegTdRaUDg&amp;t=3645s">01:00:45</a></h2>

<h3 id="automated-tests-with-accessibility-insights-with-chrome-1">Automated tests with Accessibility Insights with Chrome</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Too many issues for me to count, all with the theme itself I expect</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="keyboard-navigation-tab-stops">Keyboard navigation (tab stops)</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Missing a skip link</li>
  <li>The RTD version picker is impossible to reach</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="screen-reader-navigation-voiceover-with-safari-010545">Screen reader navigation (VoiceOver with Safari) <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8pegTdRaUDg&amp;t=3945s">01:05:45</a></h3>

<ul>
  <li>A lot of RTD issues at the theme level</li>
  <li>RTD ads are particularly poorly done</li>
  <li>There are two <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">h1</code> in the index page. Fixed in <a href="https://github.com/django-postgres-metrics/django-postgres-metrics/pull/58">#58</a>.</li>
  <li>The RTD version picker is reachable, but impossible to open</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DjangoCon Europe 2021 field notes]]></title>
    <link href="https://thib.me/djangocon-europe-field-notes"/>
    <updated>2021-06-04T06:43:49+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://thib.me/djangocon-europe-field-notes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Notes from the conference.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p><a href="https://github.com/mxsasha/lessobviouschecklist">https://github.com/mxsasha/lessobviouschecklist</a></p>

<h2 id="climate">Climate</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=upiK4du5vUI">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=upiK4du5vUI</a></p>

<p><a href="https://cloud.google.com/sustainability/region-carbon">https://cloud.google.com/sustainability/region-carbon</a>
<a href="https://pypi.org/project/energyusage/">https://pypi.org/project/energyusage/</a>
<a href="https://www.cloudcarbonfootprint.org/docs/gcp">https://www.cloudcarbonfootprint.org/docs/gcp</a>
<a href="https://codeascraft.com/2020/04/23/cloud-jewels-estimating-kwh-in-the-cloud/">https://codeascraft.com/2020/04/23/cloud-jewels-estimating-kwh-in-the-cloud/</a>
<a href="https://www.cloudcarbonfootprint.org/docs/methodology">https://www.cloudcarbonfootprint.org/docs/methodology</a>
<a href="https://github.com/hubblo-org/scaphandre">https://github.com/hubblo-org/scaphandre</a>
<a href="https://pypi.org/project/pyJoules">https://pypi.org/project/pyJoules</a></p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/responsibleproblemsolving/energy-usage/issues/16">https://github.com/responsibleproblemsolving/energy-usage/issues/16</a></p>

<h2 id="indexes">Indexes</h2>

<p>db_index=True on fields</p>

<p>class-based indexes on classes</p>

<p>Functional indexes?</p>

<p><a href="https://adamj.eu/tech/2020/07/27/how-to-modernize-your-django-index-definitions/">https://adamj.eu/tech/2020/07/27/how-to-modernize-your-django-index-definitions/</a></p>

<h2 id="database-migrations">Database migrations</h2>

<p><a href="https://speakerdeck.com/markush/writing-safe-database-migrations-djangocon-europe-2021">https://speakerdeck.com/markush/writing-safe-database-migrations-djangocon-europe-2021</a></p>

<h2 id="hunting-performance-in-django-code">Hunting Performance in Django code</h2>

<p>Tracing profilers vs sampling profilers</p>

<p>Good overview of different profiler options for Python (for example the ones that support multi-threading)</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/plasma-umass/scalene">https://github.com/plasma-umass/scalene</a></p>

<h2 id="dd-with-graphql-and-django">DD with GraphQL and Django</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.cosmicpython.com/">https://www.cosmicpython.com/</a></p>

<p>Leaner framework could be better? (FastAPI?)</p>

<h2 id="django--sphinx">Django + Sphinx</h2>

<h2 id="clean-architecture-with-django">Clean architecture with Django</h2>

<p>Best use case for Django</p>

<p>Dependency inversion</p>

<h2 id="htmx-frontend-revolution">HTMX: Frontend Revolution</h2>

<h2 id="absolutely-no-javascript">Absolutely no JavaScript</h2>

<p><a href="https://github.com/adamghill/djangocon-eu-2021-conference-talk">https://github.com/adamghill/djangocon-eu-2021-conference-talk</a></p>

<h2 id="sprint">Sprint</h2>

<p><a href="https://github.com/django/django/pull/14391">https://github.com/django/django/pull/14391</a>
<a href="https://github.com/django/django/pull/14389">https://github.com/django/django/pull/14389</a></p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/aeltanawy/Receptor">https://github.com/aeltanawy/Receptor</a></p>

<hr />

<p><a href="https://github.com/adamghill/djangocon-eu-2021-conference-talk">https://github.com/adamghill/djangocon-eu-2021-conference-talk</a></p>

<p><a href="https://code.djangoproject.com/ticket/32819">https://code.djangoproject.com/ticket/32819</a>
<a href="https://code.djangoproject.com/ticket/32820">https://code.djangoproject.com/ticket/32820</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Running remote workshops]]></title>
    <link href="https://thib.me/remote-tech-workshop-tips"/>
    <updated>2021-05-21T21:42:03+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://thib.me/remote-tech-workshop-tips</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few tips on running engaging remote training workshops, from my experience running short internal training sessions for remote teams.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="why-remote">Why remote</h2>

<p>Workshops are much harder to run remotely than in person – helping any one attendee troubleshoot their problem is hard, and helping more than one person at a time is outright impossible. Nonetheless, there are clear advantages to running workshops remotely:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Attendees can join the workshop from anywhere in the world.</li>
  <li>Even for people who are close-by, not having any travel time or logistics can be the difference between attending a session or missing it.</li>
  <li>It’s simpler for people to arrive late, or leave early.</li>
  <li>Recording is very straightforward, with all interactions happening over a video call.</li>
  <li>With no travel time or logistics, running a session multiple times is as simple as offering multiple slots.</li>
  <li>Similarly, it’s also very simple to split a curriculum over multiple smaller bookings, which might be easier to find time for than a big booking.</li>
</ul>

<p>There are specific issues to remote-ness worth highlighting as well:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Troubleshooting or offering help is hard</li>
  <li>Tech issues can get in the way – both for attendees and organisers</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="making-it-work">Making it work</h2>

<h2 id="setting-the-agenda">Setting the agenda</h2>

<p>Take ample time to document all of the steps of the workshop, including the expected duration for each. This is especially important if you’re not used to running workshops, or if you’re not used to running them remotely.</p>

<p>Remote attendance means lots of participants might be fitting the workshop around other engagements during the day, and won’t have any room for the workshop to overrun.</p>

<h2 id="preparing-sessions">Preparing sessions</h2>

<p>First and foremost, spend time getting as familiar as possible with your video call equipment and software. Spend more time with Zoom, trying out all of the options, and configuring waiting rooms, recording, and so on. Zoom has way more of those gotchas than the average video call software, so it’s good to be aware of them ahead of time.</p>

<p>Additionally,</p>

<ul>
  <li>Consider rehearsing with someone else. You pick up so many more potential gotchas if there’s someone who isn’t as experienced with the material to notice things</li>
  <li>Always share a workshop notes / supporting document ahead of time. Then you can put all the relevant links in there, as well as any specific instructions. Personally I also use that same doc as the outline of the workshop for myself. And that will be the doc I send around at the end with any extra links we discussed, and the recording if relevant. I’ll also take note of the time I expect to take for each section, so I have a sense of how I’m doing time-wise. You had slides, so it could also just be an extra “links” slide as well</li>
  <li>Ideally also have a section in that same doc with everything people should do ahead of the workshop. People might not bother ahead of time, but for those that do the workshop will be a bit easier to follow.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="during-the-session">During the session</h2>

<p>Start on time, end on time! In-between, make sure to keep to your schedule.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PyCon US 2021: Web Accessibility ♥ Python]]></title>
    <link href="https://thib.me/pycon-us-2021-python-accessibility-ftw"/>
    <updated>2021-05-13T06:43:49+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://thib.me/pycon-us-2021-python-accessibility-ftw</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a poster presentation for <a href="https://us.pycon.org/2021/">PyCon US 2021</a>, which covers two separate projects:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.curlylint.org/">Curlylint</a>, an experimental linter for HTML templates focusing on accessibility issues.</li>
  <li><a href="https://kontrasto.netlify.app/">Kontrasto</a>, a library automatically improving the contrast of text over images.</li>
</ul>

<!-- more -->

<ul>
  <li>Demo site: <a href="https://accessibility-loves-python.vercel.app/">accessibility-loves-python.vercel.app</a></li>
  <li>GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/thibaudcolas/accessibility-loves-python">thibaudcolas/accessibility-loves-python</a></li>
</ul>

<p>The poster explains what the two projects are, and offers interactive demos. For Curlylint, the demo allows linting any templates with basic configuration. For Kontrasto, users can upload an image and get the Kontrasto results.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PyCon US 2021: Building accessibility into open-source projects]]></title>
    <link href="https://thib.me/pycon-us-2021-building-accessibility-into-open-source-projects"/>
    <updated>2021-05-09T15:03:21+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://thib.me/pycon-us-2021-building-accessibility-into-open-source-projects</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a lightning talk I gave at PyCon US 2021’s <a href="https://us.pycon.org/2021/summits/maintainers/">Maintainers Summit</a>, intended for an audience of project maintainers / open-source contributors.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Video:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/9XI-8ZvU2w0" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Slides:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1qjHKEWoExYY-fG4qbRBQP_EN5fxs_8z7csVIpy9bWlg/edit">Google Slides: PyCon US 2021 - Building accessibility into open-source projects</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1hN554kNicuEvBcWK_VsiRazBTfbBGt6X/view">PDF: PyCon US 2021 - Building accessibility into open-source projects</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="transcript">Transcript</h2>

<p>Hi PyCon, thanks for having me, I’m Thibaud my pronouns are he/him and I’m a developer at Torchbox in the UK.</p>

<p>Today I’m here to talk to you about building accessibility into open source projects, and in particular coming to you with our learnings from Wagtail; I’m a core developer of this CMS called Wagtail built on Python and Django and I also contribute to Django’s accessibility team so I’m here to share with you the learnings from those two projects.</p>

<h3 id="a-wagtail-story">A Wagtail story</h3>

<p>So Wagtail is a CMS that people use to build websites.</p>

<h4 id="why-accessibility-matters-to-us">Why accessibility matters to us</h4>

<p>When it comes to why we care about accessibility there are essentially two reasons.</p>

<p>One of them is we want the Wagtail admin to be accessible to as many people as possible and the other is we want the sites actually built with Wagtail to be as accessible as possible so these are the two main reasons for end users.</p>

<h4 id="other-reasons-to-care">Other reasons to care</h4>

<p>And then as a project there are definitely a few more reasons – the big one is legislation and procurement our clients and people who pick Wagtail as a CMS definitely have very specific expectations from projects and they would pick one or the other based on requirements like this.
so yeah there is legislation in the US, in the EU, and really all around the world it’s not just those two countries.</p>

<p>One thing we do have going for ourselves is that all of those laws are based on the same standard called WCAG 2.1, the AA level being the most recent and widespread version of it.</p>

<h4 id="its-not-just-wagtail">It’s not just Wagtail</h4>

<p>And yeah it’s not just Wagtail obviously it’s not just CMSes, all types of online tools, apps, sites we build have to follow those same standards.</p>

<p>And really as developers I want to make the points that this isn’t just those projects it’s also the building blocks of those projects, the frameworks, the database modeling, the development tools, even the READMEs have to follow those same standards.</p>

<p>But yeah I don’t want this to be too negative either, so let’s look at some practical examples of where accessibility matters in the Python ecosystem in particular.</p>

<h3 id="where-accessibility-matters">Where accessibility matters</h3>

<p>I went through the <a href="https://hugovk.github.io/top-pypi-packages/">top 1000 Python packages on PyPI</a> and thought I’d pick a few examples of where you might not think of accessibility but actually there are very clear considerations to be had.</p>

<h4 id="data-science">Data science</h4>

<p>So the first one is data science, and alt text for dataviz.</p>

<p>As part of studying data you will very likely have to visualise it at some point and that might include producing images that you do want to be accessible to people who can’t actually see the visuals.</p>

<p>Of course they might not get the whole interactivity and interaction that might not be the point of your exercise but just having some form of alternative text would be useful.</p>

<h4 id="data-science-example-alt-text">Data science example: alt text</h4>

<p>So this example in particular, that comes from Matplotlib and the alt text they have defined in their example basically just restates the caption at the top of the chart.</p>

<p>Which is, well, definitely better than nothing, but to the right I have an example of what it might look like for you to consider actually going through the whole data for people who can’t see the visuals.</p>

<p>And yeah not saying this is always appropriate again but definitely something to consider and if you happen to work with one of those dataviz projects it’s important I think for this to be considered in the docs in the actual framework of how you create the visualizations, and yeah just making sure that this is taken into account.</p>

<h4 id="web-development">Web development</h4>

<p>Another important part of the Python ecosystem is web development with big frameworks that I’m sure you all have heard of before, and templating languages, and here as well, basically even though those frameworks might not always be very opinionated about HTML they do have for example code snippets in their docs that really should take accessibility into account.</p>

<p>So it’s very common for me to look at those documentation code snippets and see very basic HTML issues.</p>

<h4 id="web-development-examples-html-bad-practices">Web development examples: HTML bad practices</h4>

<p>So for example to the left here this is missing a “lang” attribute on the HTML tag.</p>

<h4 id="pdf-generation">PDF generation</h4>

<p>And here a third topic in Python in particular is PDF generation, there are lots of those projects out there and something that people might overlook is that even though the source for those PDFs is HTML, the PDF itself might not be structured at all and it might not be usable by people with screen readers, so the key feature here that I have to look for is called “tagged PDFs” and it’s a requirement that very few of those projects actually have.</p>

<p>Yeah I’m trying my best not to have this be too negative, so just to finish on a more positive note I wanted to showcase different ways you could foster those accessibility contributions on your own projects.</p>

<h3 id="fostering-contributions">Fostering contributions</h3>

<h4 id="define-your-target">Define your target</h4>

<p>The first thing to do is obviously to pick a target for what you support.</p>

<p>WCAG 2.1 at the AA level being the obvious thing to start from, and just not stop at picking the target but actually documenting it and documenting practical code review and testing steps, I think it’s very important.</p>

<p>I have added a few examples of this should you want to look into this further.</p>

<h4 id="leverage-automated-tools">Leverage automated tools</h4>

<p>And yeah now that you have this target actually doing some testing, there are lots of great automated tools out there they won’t find all of the issues but they definitely find plenty enough to get going with so I’d highly recommend looking into this.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.deque.com/axe/">Axe</a> – Accessibility rules engine with support for WCAG &amp; Section 508</li>
  <li><a href="https://accessibilityinsights.io/docs/en/web/overview">Accessibility Insights</a> – Browser extension with Axe and more</li>
  <li><a href="https://pa11y.org/">Pa11y</a> – Command line tool for accessibility checks with Axe &amp; HTML_CS</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/evcohen/eslint-plugin-jsx-a11y">eslint-plugin-jsx-a11y</a>, <a href="https://github.com/maranran/eslint-plugin-vue-a11y">eslint-plugin-vue-a11y</a>, <a href="https://github.com/YozhikM/stylelint-a11y">stylelint-a11y</a></li>
</ul>

<h4 id="leverage-automated-tools-django-example">Leverage automated tools: Django example</h4>

<p>And this is an example from Django in particular where we have this very big report that takes screenshots and logs all of the accessibility issues for different parts of the Django admin and you can just look at this and get a sense of a snapshot of how Django itself is doing.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Pa11y example: <a href="https://github.com/thibaudcolas/django_admin_tests">github.com / thibaudcolas / django_admin_tests</a></li>
</ul>

<h4 id="manual-audits">Manual audits</h4>

<p>And back on the Wagtail side we tend to invest more into manual audits just because we have the expertise to do this so these are definitely much more complex to put together and I won’t be talking about this much further but if you’re interested I can definitely talk to that a bit more.</p>

<h4 id="for-larger-projects-have-an-accessibility-team">For larger projects: have an accessibility team</h4>

<p>And yes for larger projects I definitely recommend having a dedicated team for this of subject matter experts so we have the example of the Wagtail team here but yeah for example Jupyter notebooks as well do have a team like this that looks after the accessibility of the actual notebooks which as they are used in classroom environments is very important.</p>

<p><a href="https://wagtail.org/blog/accessibility-team-reloaded/">Wagtail’s team</a> = 5 people committed for 6 months. Thank you Storm, Jesse, Kyle, Scott!</p>

<h3 id="open-source-can-lead-the-way">Open-source can lead the way</h3>

<p>So the last point I want to make really is that there are a few areas in software development like security for example where open source leads the way and shows us how it’s meant to be done basically, and I really think accessibility could be one of those areas, it really is something that matters on all projects no matter their size, and yeah that matters to a huge number of people that developers often underestimate just the sheer size of the people who can benefit from this, and yes there are well-defined standards and readily-available tools.</p>

<h3 id="thank-you-️">Thank you! ❤️</h3>

<p>Thank you I hope you enjoyed this and I’ll definitely be available later on to answer any questions.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Curlylint: Quality-of-life improvements]]></title>
    <link href="https://thib.me/curlylint-quality-of-life-improvements"/>
    <updated>2021-04-25T09:22:49+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://thib.me/curlylint-quality-of-life-improvements</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Curlylint v0.13.0 is out. It’s a relatively minor release, but comes with a few nice-to-haves for users, and a lot of behind-the-scenes project changes.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="modern-python-support">Modern Python support</h2>

<p>Curlylint now officially supports Python 3.9, and (tentatively) Python 3.10, based on the 6th alpha release. From now on, you can expect support for all Python versions <a href="https://devguide.python.org/#status-of-python-branches">actively supported by CPython maintainers</a>. In the future, this will also mean actively removing support for Python versions that reach their scheduled end-of-life.</p>

<h2 id="removed-extras-for-development-dependencies">Removed extras for development dependencies</h2>

<p>Python packaging is very messy. I’ve recently started using the <a href="https://python-poetry.org/">Poetry</a> package manager at work, primarily for the benefit of having lockfiles to pin transitive dependencies on application-style projects (a must, in my opinion). Here is an excerpt of what installing curlylint looks like in a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">poetry.lock</code>:</p>

<div class="language-ini highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nn">[[package]</span><span class="err">]</span>
<span class="py">name</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">"curlylint"</span>
<span class="py">version</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">"0.12.2"</span>
<span class="py">description</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">" Experimental HTML templates linting for Jinja, Nunjucks, Django templates, Twig, Liquid"</span>
<span class="py">category</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">"main"</span>
<span class="py">optional</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">false</span>
<span class="py">python-versions</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">"&gt;=3.6"</span>

<span class="nn">[package.dependencies]</span>
<span class="py">attrs</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">"&gt;=17.2.0"</span>
<span class="py">click</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">"&gt;=6.5"</span>
<span class="py">dataclasses</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{version = "&gt;=0.6", markers = "python_version &lt; </span><span class="se">\"</span><span class="s">3.7</span><span class="se">\"</span><span class="s">"}
parsy = "1.1.0"</span>
<span class="py">pathspec</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">"&gt;=0.6,&lt;1"</span>
<span class="py">toml</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">"&gt;=0.9.4"</span>

<span class="nn">[package.extras]</span>
<span class="py">dev</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">["black (==19.10b0)", "flake8 (==3.8.4)", "mypy (==0.812)", "pytest (==6.2.2)", "coverage (==5.4)"]</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>I find this last line very puzzling – there really should be no need for dependencies intended only for development to be visible in the published package. I don’t want curlylint’s development dependencies changing from release to release to cause noise in upgrade diffs, hence why the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">dev</code> extra has been removed.</p>

<p>It’s worth saying Poetry has otherwise been a pleasure to work with, with only a few minor inconveniences like this one. I would happily recommend it to people wanting more out of their Python package management.</p>

<h2 id="new---template-tags-cli-flag">New <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">--template-tags</code> CLI flag</h2>

<p>As the <a href="https://www.curlylint.org/docs/command-line-usage#--template-tags"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">--template-tags</code> documentation</a> now states, this makes Curlylint aware of custom tags used in templates, so the parser can understand they contain HTML content to go through.</p>

<p>This option was previously only available via a TOML configuration file, via the (now deprecated) <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">jinja-custom-elements-names</code> / <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">jinja_custom_elements_names</code> setting. The new setting works the same, but can also be set via CLI flags.</p>

<h2 id="behind-the-scenes-changes">Behind-the-scenes changes</h2>

<p>There really is only one I want to highlight – improvements to Curlylint’s test suite, which have resulted in a <a href="https://coveralls.io/github/thibaudcolas/curlylint?branch=main">14% increase in test coverage</a>. While test coverage percentages generally don’t mean much, in this case this means:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The command line interface now has unit tests. While relatively basic in the current iteration, they should be very easy to add to.</li>
  <li>The parser has more unit tests, and they are now in line with the rest of the test suite.</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://coveralls.io/github/thibaudcolas/curlylint"><img src="/images/blog/curlylint-quality-of-life-improvements/coverage-over-time.png" alt="Screen capture of the Coveralls coverage score over time as an area chart, from 59% in early March to 74% now" /></a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p><a href="https://coveralls.io/">Coveralls</a> shows coverage increasing from 59.39% in early March to 74% in late April.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Having comprehensive unit tests really matters to me as a maintainer, and from now on it should be much more realistic to expect all changes to the project to come with corresponding unit tests.</p>

<h2 id="up-next">Up next</h2>

<p>There are a lot of <a href="https://github.com/thibaudcolas/curlylint/issues?q=is%3Aissue+is%3Aopen+sort%3Aupdated-desc+label%3Aparser">parser bugs</a> I will now feel much more comfortable approaching, due to having a way to easily write tests for them.</p>

<p>Short-term, I want to make sure to get to all of the open pull request, hopefully fully clearing the backlog. I can see people are responding very well to Curlylint despite its experimental nature, and are eager to help making it more useful:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/thibaudcolas/curlylint/pull/53">#53 Optional HTML container parsing for if-else-endif type code</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/thibaudcolas/curlylint/pull/75">#75 Add test for unresolved missing alt attribute inside django block (#72)</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/thibaudcolas/curlylint/pull/76">#76 Use types_or directive for hook instead of files</a></li>
</ul>

<p>For me, the most immediate next step will be presenting Curlylint at <a href="https://us.pycon.org/2021/">PyCon US 2021</a>! I hope to get critical feedback on the tool, and am also working on an “online playground” version to try lint templates without installing anything, we should make it simpler for people to try out the linter.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2021 web conferences accepting talks]]></title>
    <link href="https://thib.me/2021-web-conferences-accepting-talks"/>
    <updated>2021-03-04T07:42:03+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://thib.me/2021-web-conferences-accepting-talks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here is a small list of conferences I put together for 2021, as I was looking for speaking opportunities, with a particular focus on Europe and America. Hope this helps!</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="djangocon-eu-2021">DjangoCon EU 2021</h2>

<p>02-06 June 2021, remote. <a href="https://2021.djangocon.eu/talks/cfp/">CFP under way</a>, ending 2020-04-01 23h59 UTC.</p>

<p>Also <a href="https://www.djangoproject.com/weblog/2021/feb/16/djangocon-europe-2021-announcement/">looking for volunteers</a> to help organise &amp; run the event.</p>

<h2 id="jsconf-budapest-2021">JSConf Budapest 2021</h2>

<p>23-24 September 2021, Budapest. <a href="https://jsconfbp.com/call-for-speakers-2021/">CFP under way</a>, ending March 31th 2021.</p>

<h2 id="djangocon-us-2021">DjangoCon US 2021</h2>

<p>October 2021, remote. <a href="https://2021.djangocon.us/">No CFP announced yet</a>.</p>

<h2 id="pycon-uk-2021">PyCon UK 2021</h2>

<p>No date announced except for “2021”. Cardiff. <a href="https://2020.pyconuk.org/">No CFP announced yet</a>.</p>

<h2 id="nordic-js-2021">Nordic JS 2021</h2>

<p>October 2021, Stockholm. <a href="https://nordicjs.com/call-for-speakers">CFP under way</a>, no deadline.</p>

<h2 id="mixit">MiXiT</h2>

<p>18-20 May 2021, Lyon, France. Looks like there might not be <a href="https://mixitconf.org/">any CFP this year</a>.</p>

<h2 id="halfstack-london-2021">HalfStack London 2021</h2>

<p>November 2021, London. <a href="https://halfstackconf.com/london/">CFP under way</a>, no deadline.</p>

<h2 id="halfstack-phoenix-2022">HalfStack Phoenix 2022</h2>

<p>January 2022, Phoenix. <a href="https://halfstackconf.com/phoenix/">CFP under way</a>, ending 15/09/2021.</p>

<h2 id="halfstack-newquay-2022">HalfStack Newquay 2022</h2>

<p>July 2022, Newquay (/ˈnjuːki/) (UK). <a href="https://halfstackconf.com/newquay/">CFP under way</a>, no deadline.</p>

<h2 id="halfstack-new-york-2022">HalfStack New York 2022</h2>

<p>August 2022, New York. <a href="https://halfstackconf.com/newyork/">CFP under way</a>, ending 30/04/2022.</p>

<h2 id="halfstack-vienna-2022">HalfStack Vienna 2022</h2>

<p>September 2022, Vienna. <a href="https://halfstackconf.com/vienna/">CFP under way</a>, ending 31/05/2022.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Accessibility team reloaded]]></title>
    <link href="https://thib.me/wagtail-accessibility-team-reloaded"/>
    <updated>2021-02-24T07:42:03+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://thib.me/wagtail-accessibility-team-reloaded</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After <a href="https://wagtail.org/blog/announcing-wagtail-sub-teams/">6 months of operations</a>, we reflect on the progress our <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail/wiki/Wagtail-sub-teams#accessibility">accessibility team</a> has made, and go on the lookout for new contributors.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="progress-to-date">Progress to date</h2>

<p>Early on, <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail/wiki/Accessibility-team#2020-07-17">we chose</a> to give priority to improvements we could make to sites built with Wagtail, rather than the Wagtail admin. Practically, this meant:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Putting together <a href="https://docs.wagtail.org/en/latest/advanced_topics/accessibility_considerations.html">Wagtail’s accessibility considerations documentation</a>, as most of the accessibility issues we identified were either dependent on how Wagtail is used, or could be worked around by implementers.</li>
  <li>From this list, we also created a <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail/projects/10">backlog of known accessibility issues</a>, which we would then proceed to fixing.</li>
</ul>

<p>Along the way, we also kept working on the <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail/issues/6107">SVG icons</a> refactoring for the admin, bit by bit.</p>

<h2 id="team-operations">Team operations</h2>

<p>We ran a short <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail/wiki/Accessibility-team#2021-01-22----team-retrospective">retrospective</a> to reflect on the team’s way of working over the last 6 months.</p>

<ul>
  <li>There were a total of 5 people involved at some point over the 6 months (Scott, Andreas, Nick, Helen, and Thibaud), but only 2 people attended each meeting on average. Not as much as we’d ideally want to.</li>
  <li>We met 9 times, for 30min each, scheduled once every two weeks.</li>
  <li>Overall we’re happy with what we’ve achieved and how the team works.</li>
  <li>We were keen to do more automated tests and manual auditing but didn’t get around to it.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-future">The future</h2>

<p>There are a few changes we will want to see over the next 6-month tenure of the team.</p>

<p><strong>We’ll want to do a new, comprehensive accessibility audit of Wagtail</strong>, either for WCAG 2.2 AA or ATAG 2.0. We want to have a clear, public record of how we’re doing.</p>

<p>We’ll review our contribution guidelines <strong>so accessibility is part and parcel of making changes to Wagtail</strong>.</p>

<p>And we’ll also investigate having <strong>automated accessibility tests built into Wagtail</strong>. <a href="https://github.com/neon-jungle/wagtail-accessibility">wagtail-accessibility</a> is one of the most popular third-party packages out there, and we want to double down on having this be one of Wagtail’s strengths.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="we-also-want-to-involve-more-people">We also want to involve more people</h3>

<p>There’s only so much we can do with two to three of us actively involved – ideally we’d want a team twice that size! All are welcome regardless of skill level or background, and the time commitment is very reasonable. We’re particularly keen to work with people who:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Have personal experience of access and functional needs, or who are regular users of assistive technologies.</li>
  <li>Work on User Experience, design, or content – and can help us understand the needs of our users.</li>
</ul>

<p>And of course web developers who want to have a practical impact on making the web more accessible!</p>

<p>Does this sound like your kind of jam? If you’re keen to learn more, <a href="https://github.com/wagtail/wagtail/wiki/Slack">reach out to us on Slack</a> in #accessibility.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
